In this video we will be looking at
Coulomb's
law and what it does.
So what is Coulomb's law? Coulomb's law
basically
gives the electric force between two point
charges.
And that's really important because a lot
of
the times there will be a relation between
electrostatics
and forces or kinematics and it tells you
the
magnitude of the force and whether the
force
is attractive or repulsive. So the sign.
So whether the force, but the force if
it's
attractive or repulsive just a good thing
to
remember is just to know that forces repel
and
opposite forces attract. So what is the
equation
of Coulomb's law? Well the Coulomb's law
states that the force, the electrostatic
force,
is equal to the Coulombic constant, which
I'll
talk about later, times the two charges,
the
magnitude of the product of the two
charges,
over the distance squared.
And F is obviously the force in newtons.
K is the Coulombic attraction or Coulombic
constant.
And it's the same for all formulae.
And it's equal to 8.99 times 10 to the 9
newtons
times metres squared over Coulomb's
squared.
Q1 and Q2 are the charges.
So it's measured in Coulomb's.
And R is the distance between the two
charges.
Distance between charges in metres.
So a lot of the times they're going to
give
you the distance in let's say nanometres
or
picometres. So you're going to have to
remember
how to convert those back to metres.
And this is Coulomb's law. And it's
probably
given in your formula sheet. Now basically
this
is a force and you know whether it's
attractive
or repulsive because like charges distract
and
opposite charges repel. So if Q1, the sine
of
Q1 times the sine of Q2 is equal to, I'll
just write it like this, Q1, that would be
the
sine over Q2, that would be the sine.
If both of these are the same, then that
means
they're going to repel. But if they're
different,
times Q2 over Q2, if they're different,
that
means that they're going to attract. And
it's
a pretty straightforward way of telling
whether
they repel or attract. And you can use
Coulomb's
law directly when either charges are point
charges,
so they take up no space, they're just
charges
in the grid or in the coordinate point
charges. Or the objects or the particles
are
very small. Very small compared to the
distance.
Because it depends on the distance.
And if you're talking about two big
objects,
then the radius will be way bigger than
the
distance between. So objects are very
small
compared to distance. And a lot of the
questions
ask you to calculate, let's say, the
forces
exerted on an object surrounded by
multiple
charges. And if multiple charges are
present,
we might go over an example for this. If
we
want to calculate the force exerted from
each
charge, because they're vectors, calculate
f
from each charge.
Usually they're going to be point charges.
And
then you get the net force at the end
using
trigonometry. Or basically you add the
forces,
because they're vectors. Add forces to get
net
force. So here's a really simple example.
Let's say we have a positive point charge.
So we have a positive point charge over
here
with a charge of, let's say, 5 Coulombs.
And then we have, let's say, another
positive
point charge with a charge of 10 Coulombs.
And we have a positively charged particle,
let's
say, with a charge of 3 Coulombs.
Now we want to try to find its
acceleration
and in what direction. So basically you
have
to use, you have to get the net force
exerted
on each of these positive charges. So
let's
call this charge A, let's call this charge
B,
and we'll just directly use Coulomb's law.
Let's say they're both, this charge is 3
times
10 to the negative 9 metres apart. And
this
charge is 4 times 10 to the negative 9
metres
apart. So we know that, let's first
calculate
the charge exerted for charge A.
Well, charge A, these are both positive
charges.
So charge A is going to exert a force to
the
right. So the free-body diagram of this
particle
would be F A and F B.
We don't know the magnitude yet, but we
know
that F B is going to exert a force this
way.
And F A is going to exert a force this
way,
because they're same signs.
So F A equals, the constant is 8.99 times
to the 9, 8.99 times 10 to the 9.
The magnitude or the absolute value of Q1
would
be, Q1 let's say would be the charge of A,
really
doesn't matter, 5 times 3 over, what's the
distance?
It's 4 times 10 to the negative 9 squared.
And that, when you type it in your
calculator,
you're going to get a force, and that
should
be in Newtons. 15 over 4 times 10 to the
negative
9 squared. And you would get 8.43 times 10
to
the 27 Newtons. Now this is probably not
that
realistic, this is a really massive force,
but
for the sake, I've just made up the
quantities
for the sake of this question, let's just
go
with it. The force of B, so force of A,
this
is going to have a force exerted on this
that
is this massive value, 8.43 times 10 to
the
27 Newtons. And then we have to calculate
force
B, and then we have to get the net force.
And then we use Newtons law. Force B, same
thing,
8.99 times 10 to the 9 times 3 times 10
over
3 times 10 to the negative 9 squared.
And when you do that, you would get 2.00
times 10 to the 28 Newtons.
So force B would obviously be a greater
force
than force A. But by how much?
Well the net force, the total net force is
equal
to force A minus force B.
Or plus force B, but then force B is
negative
because it's in the opposite direction. So
8.43
times 10 to the 27 plus negative 3.00
times
10 to the 28. And that would be equal to
8.43
times 10 to the 27 minus this. You'd get a
net
force of negative 2.15 times 10 to the 28
Newtons.
It's negative because it's going in the
left
direction, because there's a greater force
of
B. So it's going to go this way with a
force
of this magnitude. And basically now that
we
have the force, we can calculate the
acceleration.
Let's say the question gave us a mass.
Doesn't really matter, I'll just call it x
for
simplicity's sake. We know force net
equals
mass times net acceleration. So
acceleration
is F net over mass, which is negative 2.15
times
10 to the 28 over x.
And that would be your final acceleration.
It really depends on what the question
gives
you. But that's basically how you deal
with
multiple charges, and how you use
Coulomb's
law to calculate the multiple charges. And
that's
all for today's video. I hope you've
learned
how to calculate these types of questions
with
Coulomb's law. And I hope you enjoyed!
Thank you for watching, and we'll see you
in
the next one. Bye!